<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-anderson-v6ops-siit-dc-2xlat-00"
     ipr="trust200902">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="SIIT-DC-2XLAT">SIIT-DC: Dual Translation Mode</title>
    <author fullname="Tore Anderson" initials="T.A." surname="Anderson">
      <organization>Redpill Linpro</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Vitaminveien 1A</street>
          <city>0485 Oslo</city>
          <country>NORWAY</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+47 959 31 212</phone>
        <email>tore@redpill-linpro.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2014" />
    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>IPv6 Operations</workgroup>
    <abstract>
      <t>
      This document describes an extension of the <xref
      target="I-D.anderson-v6ops-siit-dc">SIIT-DC</xref> architecture, which
      allows applications that are incompatible with SIIT and/or Network
      Address Translation in general to operate correctly in an SIIT-DC
      environment.
      </t>
      <t>
      The reader is expected to be familiar with the SIIT-DC architecture
      described in <xref target="I-D.anderson-v6ops-siit-dc"/>.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
      <xref target="I-D.anderson-v6ops-siit-dc">SIIT-DC</xref> describes an
      architecture where IPv4-only users can access IPv6-only services through
      a stateless translation gateway. However, this only works for
      applications that are compatible with Network Address Translation (NAT),
      due to the fact that the SIIT Gateway will rewrite the addresses in the
      IP header as part of the translation process. SIIT-DC will also fail to
      work correctly for applications that make use of legacy IPv4-only socket
      calls.
      </t>
      <t>
      This document remedies this problem by defining an extension to SIIT-DC.
      Translations performed by the SIIT Gateway will also be done in reverse
      by an SIIT Host Agent running on the server. The resulting IPv4 packets
      are then passed to the application. This way, the application will be
      able to use legacy IPv4-only socket calls and/or include references to
      its own IPv4 address in the application payload, while maintaining
      correct operation.
      </t>
      <t>
      The approach is heavily inspired by and very similar to <xref
      target="RFC6877">464XLAT</xref>. The SIIT Host Agent described in this
      document is almost identical to the CLAT component in 464XLAT, except
      for the fact that it will be located on a server, rather than on the
      customer-side node. Furthermore, an SIIT Host Agent uses statically
      configured public IP addresses, whereas a 464XLAT CLAT uses a dynamic
      IPv6 address and a private IPv4 address. The SIIT Gateway described in
      <xref target="I-D.anderson-v6ops-siit-dc"/> is used instead of the PLAT
      described by 464XLAT.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
      <t>
      This document makes use of the following terms:
      </t>
      <t>
      <list style="hanging">
       <t hangText="IPv4 Service Address">A public IPv4 address with which
       IPv4-only clients will communicate. This communication will be
       translated to IPv6 by the SIIT Gateway.</t>
       <t hangText="IPv6 Service Address">A public IPv6 address assigned to a
       server or application in the IPv6 network. IPv6-only and dual stacked
       clients communicates with this address directly without invoking SIIT.
       IPv4-only clients also communicates with this address through the SIIT
       Gateway and via an IPv4 Service Address.</t>
       <t hangText="SIIT Host Agent">A logical function very similar to an
       SIIT Gateway that resides on a server and provides virtual IPv4
       connectivity to applications, by performing <xref target="RFC6145"/>
       translation on packets passing through it. See <xref
       target="siit_ha_spec"/>.</t>
       <t hangText="SIIT Gateway">A device or a logical function that
       translates between IPv4 and IPv6 in accordance with <xref
       target="RFC6145"/> and <xref target="I-D.anderson-v6ops-siit-dc"/>.</t>
       <t hangText="Static Address Mapping">A bi-directional mapping between
       an IPv4 Service Address and an IPv6 Service Address configured in the
       SIIT Gateway. When translating between IPv4 and IPv6, the SIIT Gateway
       changes the adddress fields in the translated packet's IP header
       according to any matching Static Address Mapping.</t>
       <t hangText="Translation Prefix">An IPv6 prefix into which the entire
       IPv4 address space is mapped. This prefix is routed to the SIIT
       Gateway's IPv6 interface. It is either an Network-Specific Prefix or a
       Well-Known Prefix as specified in <xref target="RFC6052"/>. When
       translating between IPv4 and IPv6, the SIIT Gateway prepends or strips
       the Translation Prefix from the address fields in the translated
       packet's IP header, unless a Static Address Mapping exists for the IP
       address in question.</t>
     </list>
     </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="siit_ha_spec" title="SIIT Host Agent Specification">
      <t>
      The SIIT Host Agent runs on the servers hosting application which do not
      work correctly with the SIIT-DC architecture as specified by <xref
      target="I-D.anderson-v6ops-siit-dc"/>. Its task is the performing the
      exact same packet translation as the SIIT Gateway, only in reverse. It
      therefore shares the same implementation requirements as the SIIT
      Gateway defined in Section 4 of <xref
      target="I-D.anderson-v6ops-siit-dc"/>, with one exception: The SIIT Host
      Agent is not required to support configuring an arbitrary number of
      static mappings, but it must support at least one.
      </t>
      <t>
      The SIIT Host Agent must be configured with a Static Address Mapping
      that corresponds exactly with the same mapping found on the SIIT
      Gateway. The IPv4 address of the Static Address Mapping (i.e., the IPv4
      Service Address) must be configured on a virtual network interface which
      applications running on the server can bind to, and the server is
      expected to install a default IPv4 route poining to this virtual IPv4
      interface. The IPv6 address of the Static Address Mapping must be a
      secondary address that is routed to the server by the IPv6 network. The
      server must forward all packets it receives destined for this IPv6
      address to the SIIT Host Agent.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Architectural Overview">
      <t>
      The following figure shows how an application (that is presumably
      incompatible with standard SIIT-DC) is being made available to the IPv4
      Internet on the IPv4 address 192.0.2.2. The application will be able to
      know that this is its local address and thus be able to provide correct
      references to it in application payload.
      </t>
      <t>
      The figure also shows how the same application is available over IPv6 on
      its IPv6 Service Address 2001:db8:12:34::2. This is included in order to
      illustrate how native IPv6 connectivity is not impacted by the SIIT Host
      Agent, and also to illustrate how the address assigned to the SIIT Host
      Agent (2001:db8:12:34::3) is separate from the primary IPv6 address of
      the server. It is however important to note that the application in
      question does not have to be dual-stack capable at all. IPv4-only
      applications would also be able to operate behind a SIIT Host Agent in
      the exact same manner.
      </t>
      <t>
      Note that the figure below could be considered a more detailed view of
      Customer A's FTP server from the example topology figure in <xref
      target="I-D.anderson-v6ops-siit-dc">Appendix A of
      I-D.anderson-v6ops-siit-dc</xref>. Both figures intentionally use the
      exact same example IP addresses and prefixes.
      </t>
      <t>
      <figure anchor="fig_architecture" align="center">
        <preamble>SIIT Host Agent Architecture</preamble>
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
  +-------------------+         +----------------+
  | IPv6-capable user |         | IPv4-only user |
  | ================= |         | ============== |
  |                   |         |                |
  +-<2001:db8::ab:cd>-+         +-<203.0.113.50>-+
      |                                  |
      |                                  |
   (the IPv6 internet)         (the IPv4 Internet)
      |                                  |
      |                                  |
      |        +------------------<192.0.2.0/24>-+
      |        |                                 |
      |        |           SIIT Gateway          |
      |        |           ============          |
      |        |                                 |
      |        |       Translation Prefix:       |
      |        |         2001:db8:46::/96        |
      |        |                                 |
      |        |     Static Address Mapping:     |
      |        | 192.0.2.2 <=> 2001:db8:12:34::3 |
      |        |                                 |
      |        +--------------<2001:db8:46::/96>-+
      |                               |
      |                               |
     (the IPv6-only data centre network)
      |                               |
      |                               |
+--<2001:db8:12:34::2>-------<2001:db8:12:34::3>---+
|     |                               |            |
|     |          IPv6-only server     |            |
|     |          ================     |            |
|     |                               |            |
|     |        +-------------<2001:db8:12:34::3>-+ |
|     |        |                                 | |
|     |        |         SIIT Host Agent         | |
|     |        |         ===============         | |
|     |        |                                 | |
|     |        |       Translation Prefix:       | |
|     |        |         2001:db8:46::/96        | |
|     |        |                                 | |
|     |        |     Static Address Mapping:     | |
|     |        | 192.0.2.2 <=> 2001:db8:12:34::3 | |
|     |        |                                 | |
|     |        +---------------------<192.0.2.2>-+ |
|     |                                   |        |
|     |                                   |        |
| +-[2001:db8:12:34::2]--------------[192.0.2.2]-+ |
| |      AF_INET6                      AF_INET   | |
| |                                              | |
| |           Dual-stacked application           | |
| |                                              | |
| +----------------------------------------------+ |
+--------------------------------------------------+
        ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Deployment Considerations">
      <section anchor="ipv6_pmtu" title="IPv6 Path MTU">
        <t>
        The IPv6 Path MTU between the SIIT Host Agent and the SIIT Gateway
        will typically be larger than the default value defined in Section 4
        of <xref target="RFC6145"/> (1280), as it will typically contained
        within a single administrative domain. Therefore, it is recommended
        that the IPv6 Path MTU configured in the SIIT Host Agent is raised
        accordingly. It is RECOMMENDED that the SIIT Host Agent and the SIIT
        Gateway use identical configured IPv6 Path MTU values.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="ipv4_mtu" title="IPv4 MTU">
        <t>
        In order to avoid fragmentation, it is RECOMMENDED that the virtual
        IPv4 interface is configured with an MTU value identical to the
        configured IPv6 Path MTU - 20. This ensures that the application may
        do its part in avoiding IP-level fragmentation from occurring, e.g.,
        by segmenting/fragmenting outbound packets at the application layer,
        and advertising the maximum size its peer may use for inbound packets
        (e.g., through the use of the TCP MSS option).
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
      The author would like to especially thank the authors of <xref
      target="RFC6877">464XLAT</xref>: Masataka Mawatari, Masanobu Kawashima,
      and Cameron Byrne. The architecture described by this document is merely
      an adaptation of their work to a data centre environment, and could not
      have happened without them.
      </t>
      <t>
      The author would like also to thank the following individuals for their
      contributions, suggestions, corrections, and criticisms: Fred Baker,
      Tobias Brox, [YOUR NAME GOES HERE].
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>
      The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
      This draft makes no request of the IANA. The RFC Editor may remove this
      section prior to publication.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
      This section discusses security considerations specific to the use of a
      SIIT Host Agent. See the <xref
      target="I-D.anderson-v6ops-siit-dc">Security Considerations in
      I-D.anderson-v6ops-siit-dc</xref> for additional security considerations
      applicable to the SIIT-DC architecture in general.
      </t>
      <section anchor="sec_loops" title="Address Spoofing">
        <t>
        If the SIIT Host Agent receives an IPv4 packet from the application
        from a different source address than the one it has a Static Address
        Mapping for, the both the source and destination addresses will be
        rewritten according to <xref target="RFC6052"/>. After undergoing the
        reverse translation in the SIIT Gateway, the resulting IPv4 packet
        routed to the IPv4 network will have a spoofed IPv4 source address.
        The SIIT Host Agent should therefore ensure that ingress filtering
        (cf. <xref target="RFC2827">BCP38</xref> is used on the SIIT Host
        Agent's IPv4 interface, so that such packets are immediately
        discarded.
        </t>
        <t>
        If the SIIT Host Agent receives an IPv6 packet with both the source
        and destination address equal to the one it has a static mapping from,
        the resulting packet would appear to the application as locally
        generated, as both the source address and the destination address will
        be the same address as the one configured on the virtual IPv4
        interface. This could trick the application into thinking this packet
        came from a trusted source, and give elevated privileges accordingly.
        To prevent this, the SIIT Host Agent should discard any received IPv6
        packets that have a source address that is equal either to either the
        IPv4 (after undergoing <xref target="RFC6052"/> translation) or the
        IPv6 address in the static mapping.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <!-- replace the below with
	   <?rfc include="reference.I-D.anderson-v6ops-siit-dc"?> once the
           drafts have been uploaded to the IETF web site -->
      <reference anchor='I-D.anderson-v6ops-siit-dc'>
          <front>
	  <title>SIIT-DC: Stateless IP/ICMP Translation in IPv6 Data Centre
          Environments</title>
          <author initials='T' surname='Anderson' fullname='Tore Anderson'>
            <organization />
          </author>
          <date month='September' day='5' year='2014' />
	  <abstract><t>This document describes the use of Stateless IP/ICMP
	  Translation (SIIT) in data centre environments in order to
	  simultaneously facilitate IPv6 deployment and IPv4 address
	  conservation. It describes the overall architecture, and provides
	  guidelines for both operators and implementers.</t></abstract>
        </front>
	<seriesInfo name='Internet-Draft'
	            value='draft-anderson-v6ops-siit-dc-00' />
	<format type='TXT'
	        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-anderson-v6ops-siit-dc-00.txt'
	/>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2827"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6052"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6145"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6877"?>
    </references>
  </back>

</rfc>
<!-- Change Log
v00 2014-08-05	tore	Initial version
-->
<!-- vim: syntax=xml tw=78 ai fo=2 et:
-->
