<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-anderson-v6ops-siit-eam-00" ipr="trust200902">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="SIIT-EAM">Explicit Address Mappings for Stateless IP/ICMP
    Translation</title>
    <author fullname="Tore Anderson" initials="T" surname="Anderson">
      <organization>Redpill Linpro</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>Vitaminveien 1A</street>
          <city>0485 Oslo</city>
          <country>NORWAY</country>
        </postal>
        <phone>+47 959 31 212</phone>
        <email>tore@redpill-linpro.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year="2014" />
    <area>General</area>
    <workgroup>IPv6 Operations</workgroup>
    <abstract>
      <t>
      This document extends the Stateless IP/ICMP Translation Algorithm (SIIT)
      with an Explicit Address Mapping algorithm. This algorithm facilitates
      stateless IP/ICMP translation between arbitrary (non-IPv4-translatable)
      IPv6 endpoints and IPv4.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>
      The <xref target="RFC6145">Stateless IP/ICMP Translation Algorithm
      (SIIT)</xref> specifies that when translating IPv4 addresses to IPv6 and
      vice versa, all addresses must be translated using the algorithm
      specified in <xref target="RFC6052"/>. This document specifies an
      alternative to the <xref target="RFC6052"/> algorithm, where IP
      addresses are translated according to a table of Explicit Address
      Mappings configured on the stateless translator. This removes the
      previous constraint that IPv6 nodes that communicate with IPv4 nodes
      through SIIT must be configured with IPv4-translatable IPv6 addresses.
      </t>
      <t>
      The Explicit Address Mapping Table does not replace <xref
      target="RFC6052"/>. For most use cases, is expected that both algorithms
      are used in concert. The Explicit Address Mapping algorithm is used only
      when a mapping matching the address to be translated exists. If no
      matching mapping exists, the <xref target="RFC6052"/> algorithm will be
      used instead. In a typical deployment, when translating a single IPv4
      packet to IPv6, the destination address will be translated according to
      an Explicit Address Mapping while the source address will be translated
      according to <xref target="RFC6052"/>, and vice versa when translating
      from IPv6 to IPv4.
      </t>
      <section anchor="terminology" title="Terminology">
        <t>
        This document makes use of the following terms:
        </t>
        <t>
        <list style="hanging">
         <t hangText="EAM">An Explicit Address Mapping, as specified in <xref
         target="eam_def"/>.</t>
         <t hangText="EAMT">The Explicit Address Mapping Table, as specified
         in <xref target="eam_def"/>.</t>
         <t hangText="SIIT">The Stateless IP/ICMP Translation algorithm, as
         specified in <xref target="RFC6145"/>.</t>
         <t hangText="IPv4-converted IPv6 addresses">As defined in Section 1.3
         of <xref target="RFC6052"/>.</t>
         <t hangText="IPv4-translatable IPv6 addresses">As defined in Section
         1.3 of <xref target="RFC6052"/>.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>
        The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119"/>.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="problemstatement" title="Problem Statement">
      <t>
      Section 3.2.1 of <xref target="RFC6144"/> notes that "stateless
      translation mechanisms typically put constraints on what IPv6 addresses
      can be assigned to IPv6 nodes that want to communicate with IPv4
      destinations using an algorithmic mapping". In practice, this means that
      the IPv6 nodes must be configured with IPv4-translatable IPv6 addresses.
      For the reasons discussed below, some environments may find that the use
      of IPv4-translatable IPv6 addresses is not desired or even possible.
      </t>
      <t>
      <list style="hanging">
       <t hangText="Limited availability">The number of IPv4-translatable IPv6
       addresses available to an operator is equal to the number of IPv4
       addresses he assigns to the SIIT function. IPv4 addresses are scarce,
       and as a result a operator might not have enough IPv4-translatable IPv6
       addresses to number his entire IPv6 infrastructure.</t>
       <t hangText="Restricted format">IPv4-translatable IPv6 addresses must
       conform to the format specified in Section 2.2 of <xref
       target="RFC6052"/>. This format is not compatible with other common
       IPv6 address formats, such as the EUI-64 based IPv6 address format used
       by <xref target="RFC4862">IPv6 Stateless Address
       Autoconfiguration</xref>.</t>
      </list>
      </t>
      <t>
      An operator could overcome the above two problems by building an IPv6
      network using regular (non-IPv4-translatable) IPv6 addresses, and assign
      IPv4-translatable IPv6 addresses as secondary addresses on the nodes
      that want to communicate with IPv4 nodes through SIIT only. However,
      doing so may result in a new set of undesired properties:
      </t>
      <t>
      <list style="hanging">
       <t hangText="Routing complexity">The IPv4-translatable IPv6 addresses
       must be routed throughout the IPv6 network separately from the primary
       (non-IPv4-translatable) IPv6 addresses used by the nodes. These routes
       might not be aggregatable, as two adjacent IPv4-translatable IPv6
       addresses might not be assigned to two adjacent IPv6 nodes. As a
       result, in order to support SIIT, the IPv6 network might need to carry
       a large number of unaggregatable routes. These routes must be
       separately injected into the IPv6 routing topology somehow. Any
       intermediate devices in the IPv6 network such as a firewall might
       require special configuration in order to treat the IPv4-translatable
       IPv6 address the same as the primary IPv6 address, for example by
       requiring that any ACL entries involving the primary IPv6 address of a
       node must be duplicated.</t>
       <t hangText="Operational complexity">The IPv4-translatable IPv6
       addresses must not only be assigned to the IPv6 nodes participating in
       SIIT, all applications and services on those nodes must also be
       configured to use them. For example, if the IPv6 node is a load
       balancer, it might require a separate Virtual Server definition using
       the IPv4-translatable IPv6 address in addition to one using the
       service's primary IPv6 address. A web server might require specific
       configuration to listen for connections on both the IPv4-translatable
       and the primary IPv6 address. A High-Availability cluster service must
       be set up to fail over both addresses between cluster nodes, and
       depending on how the IPv6 network learns the location of the
       IPv4-translatable IPv6 address, the fail-over mechanism used for the
       two addresses might be completely different. Service monitoring must be
       done for both the IPv4-translatable and the primary IPv6 address, and
       any trouble-shooting procedures must be extended to involved both
       addresses.</t>
      </list>
      </t>
      <t>
      In short, the use of IPv4-translatable IPv6 addresses in parallel with
      regular IPv6 addresses is in many ways analogous to the use of <xref
      target="RFC4213">Dual Stack</xref>. While no actual IPv4 packets are
      used, the IPv4-translatable IPv6 addresses creates a secondary "stack"
      in the infrastructure that must be treated and operated separately from
      the primary one. This increases the complexity of the overall
      infrastructure, in turn increasing operational overhead, and reducing
      reliability. An operator who for such reasons finds the use Dual Stack
      unappealing, might feel the same way about using SIIT with
      IPv4-translatable IPv6 addresses. 
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="eam_def" title="Explicit Address Mapping Algorithm">
      <t>
      This normative section defines the EAM algorithm. SIIT implementations
      are REQUIRED to support the specifications herein.
      </t>
      <section anchor="eam_tbl" title="Explicit Address Mapping Table">
        <t>
        An SIIT implementation MUST include an Explicit Address Mapping Table
        (EAMT). By default, the EAMT SHOULD be empty. The operator MUST be
        able to populate the EAMT using the implementation's normal
        configuration interfaces. The implementation MAY additionally support
        other ways of populating the EAMT.
        </t>
        <t>
        The EAMT consists of the following columns:
        </t>
        <t>
        <list>
          <t>IPv4 Prefix</t>
          <t>IPv6 Prefix</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>
        SIIT implementations MAY include other columns in order to support
        proprietary extensions to the EAM algorithm.
        </t>
        <t>
        Throughout this document, figures representing the EAMT contain an
        Index column using the pound sign as the header. This column is not a
        required part of this specification; it is included only as a
        convenience to the reader.
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="eam_types" title="Explicit Address Mapping Specification">
        <t>
        An EAM consists of an IPv4 Prefix and an IPv6 Prefix. The prefix
        length MAY be omitted, in which case the implementation MUST assume it
        to be 32 for IPv4 and 128 for IPv6.
        </t>
        <t>
        <figure anchor="fig_eam_table" align="center">
        <preamble>Example Explicit Address Mapping Table</preamble>
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+---+--------------+-----------------+
| # | IPv4 Prefix  |   IPv6 Prefix   |
+---+--------------+-----------------+
| 1 | 192.0.2.1    | 2001:db8::      |
| 2 | 192.0.2.2/32 | 2001:db8::2/128 |
| 3 | 192.0.2.3    | 2001:db8::3     |
| 4 | 192.0.2.4/30 | 2001:db8::8/126 |
+---+--------------+-----------------+
        ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        </t>
        <t>
        A stateless IP/ICMP translator MUST behave as follows:
        </t>
        <t>
        <list style="symbols">
          <t>When translating an IPv4/ICMPv4 packet to IPv6, the SIIT
          implementation MUST first look up the IPv4 addresses to be
          translated in the IPv4 Prefix column in the EAMT. If a matching EAM
          entry is found, the address MUST be translated to the entry's IPv6
          Prefix value.</t>
          <t>When translating an IPv6/ICMPv6 packet to IPv4, the SIIT
          implementation MUST first look up the IPv6 addresses to be
          translated in the IPv6 Prefix column in the EAMT. If a matching EAM
          entry is found, the address MUST be translated to the entry's IPv4
          Prefix value.</t>
          <t>If no matching EAM is found, the SIIT implementation MUST proceed
          to translate the packet in accordance with <xref target="RFC6145"/>
          (and its updates).</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>
        An EAM's IPv4 Prefix and IPv6 Prefix MUST have identical suffix
        lengths. Any suffix bits MUST be kept intact during translation. 
        </t>
        <t>
        Overlapping EAMs SHOULD be considered an error, and attempts to insert
        them into the EAM table SHOULD be blocked. The behaviour of an SIIT
        implementation when overlapping EAMs are present in the EAM table is
        left undefined.
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Lack of Checksum Neutrality">
      <t>
      When one or both of the address fields in an IP/ICMP packet are
      translated according to EAM, the translation can not be relied upon to
      be checksum neutral, even if the well-known prefix 64:ff9b::/96 is used.
      This consideration is discussed in more detail in Section 4.1 of <xref
      target="RFC6052"/>. 
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>
      The EAM algorithm does not introduce any new security issues beyond
      those that are already discussed in Section 7 of <xref
      target="RFC6145"/>.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>
      This draft makes no request of the IANA. The RFC Editor may remove this
      section prior to publication.
      </t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="acks" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
      This document was conceived due to comments made by Dave Thaler in the
      v6ops session at IETF 91 as well as e-mail discussions between Fred
      Baker and the author.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6052"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6145"?>
    </references>
    <references title="Informative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4213"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4862"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6144"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6877"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7335"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.anderson-v6ops-siit-dc"?>
    </references>
    <section anchor="usecases" title="Use Cases">
      <t>
      The following subsections lists some use cases that leverage SIIT with
      the EAM algorithm at the time of writing.
      </t>
      <section anchor="usecase_464xlat" title="464XLAT">
        <t>
        When the CLAT component in the <xref target="RFC6877">464XLAT</xref>
        architecture does not have a dedicated IPv6 prefix assigned, it may
        instead use "one interface IPv6 address that is claimed by the CLAT".
        This IPv6 address might not be IPv4-translatable. If this is the case,
        the CLAT essentially implements the EAM algorithm using an EAMT as
        follows (assuming the CLAT's IPv4 address is picked from the <xref
        target="RFC7335">IPv4 Service Continuity Prefix</xref>):
        </t>
        <t>
        <figure anchor="fig_eamt_464xlat" align="center">
        <preamble>Example EAMT for an 464XLAT CLAT</preamble>
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+---+--------------+-------------------------------+
| # | IPv4 Prefix  |          IPv6 Prefix          |
+---+--------------+-------------------------------+
| 1 | 192.0.0.1/32 | CLAT_claimed_IPv6_address/128 |
+---+--------------+-------------------------------+
        ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="usecase_siit_dc" title="SIIT-DC">
        <t>
        <xref target="I-D.anderson-v6ops-siit-dc">SIIT-DC</xref> describes the
        use of SIIT to facilitate connectivity from the IPv4 Internet to
        services hosted in an IPv6-only data centre. In order to avoid the
        constraints relating to the use of IPv4-translatable IPv6 addresses
        discussed in <xref target="problemstatement"/> the stateless IPv4/IPv6
        translators are provisioned with an EAMT containing one entry per
        IPv6-only service that are to be made available from the IPv4
        Internet, for example (assuming 2001:db8:aaaa::1 and 2001:db8:bbbb::1
        are assigned to load balancers or servers that provides the IPv6-only
        services in question):
        </t>
        <t>
        <figure anchor="fig_eamt_siit_dc" align="center">
        <preamble>Example EAMT for SIIT-DC</preamble>
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+---+--------------+----------------------+
| # | IPv4 Prefix  |     IPv6 Prefix      |
+---+--------------+----------------------+
| 1 | 192.0.2.1/32 | 2001:db8:aaaa::1/128 |
| 2 | 192.0.2.2/32 | 2001:db8:bbbb::1/128 |
+---+--------------+----------------------+
        ]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </back>

</rfc>
<!-- vim: syntax=xml tw=78 ai fo=2 et:
-->
